Hey everyone, thanks for dropping back
into the macroverse.
Today, we're going to talk about how the
Federal Reserve held interest rates at
3.75%
and the implications of that on the bond
market and risk assets. If you guys like
the content, make sure you subscribe to
the channel, give the video a thumbs up,
and also check out the sale on Into the
Cryptoverse Premium at
intothecryptoverse.com.
If you do enjoy these more macro
discussions about how it's affecting
investing in different asset classes, I
think you would like coming to the first
ITC conference taking place in Miami on
November 20th through the 22nd. So, make
sure you guys check that out. Link is in
the description below.
We're going to be raising those prices
in a few weeks, so make sure you guys
get your ticket in the meantime. Let's
go ahead and jump in. So, we just did a
video yesterday saying that the Fed was
unlikely to hike rates in July. Now,
there were some banks thinking that it
might actually happen, but you know, the
the markets didn't think it was going to
happen. They said about a 2/3 chance
they would hold constant, and in fact,
they did. And what we said was what made
the most amount of sense
from that ties everything in to like the
business cycle and a potential
correction coming by the S&P 500, which
normally happens in the back half of
midterm years, and then a future market
cycle bottom by Bitcoin, how it all ties
together.
And what we said was it would make the
most amount of sense
if you need a narrative, not that you
need one,
but if you require a narrative, the
narrative is just simply the Fed doesn't
cut or they don't Sorry, they don't
raise rates at the July meeting.
And because they don't raise rates,
the bond market starts to revolt.
And sure enough,
look at the 30-year yield today.
The 30-year yield has been trying to get
through 5.2%
for years, right? Ever since really
October 2023 when it hit that level. And
now
the Fed was unwilling to raise rates.
And
what happened is
the bond
vigilantes
are revolting. And they're saying, "No,
we used to be more worried about
inflation
than the labor market." Now, I know what
some of you guys are thinking, right?
Oh, inflation's not an issue. Why why
worry about inflation?
But there's a lot There's a reality here
of There's just a lot of uncertainty
about inflation, right? I mean, yes, oil
has come down, which is a good thing,
right? I mean, oil has dropped a lot,
but look at you know, look at XLE. This
is something that I I've talked about
for a while. Look at this thing. And
look at how
I mean, it it wasn't even that far away
from a new high just a just yesterday,
basically 2 days ago.
There's a lot of uncertainty in you
know, in the energy markets. And
normally, from a business cycle
perspective, energy is one of the last
things to top.
Right?
And we haven't even had the IPOs by
OpenAI, etc. So, you would thought that
sort of is like this future thing. So,
I I I think as it you know, as we think
about Sorry, I need to make this
Hold on a second. Sorry about that. Uh
wow, I'm going to get a lot of
complaints about that. The video my
video being large. Um
when you think about it, right?
This all makes sense. The Fed doesn't
hike.
The bond vigilantes revolt. And they're
like,
"Oh,
>> [laughter]
>> you no way, right? Oh, hell no. You you
you can't get away with this.
The 30-year yield breaks out.
The 10-year yield
What did we say the 10-year yield would
do? That it would head back to where it
was in October 2023. It's on its way.
That TLT
we go sweep the lows from October of
2023 and guess where it's headed? To
those lows.
It all makes sense. And so, what I what
I could see happening
is if
the labor market data still comes in
strong. And I know people like, "Well,
the labor market isn't that strong."
I kind of agree with you in some sense.
Like, they're not hiring. There's not a
lot of hiring. There's not a lot of job
openings. But, the reality is there's
also not a lot of layoffs.
If there were a lot of layoffs, initial
claims wouldn't be so low. I mean, the
last time initial claims were at like
187,000
was what? Like, five decades ago or
something?
Yes, it can change quickly. But, the
problem for the Fed is that
you have a labor market that is heating
up in the sense that you're not really
seeing layoffs. The unemployment rate
has been coming back down. And one of
the reasons that inflation was starting
to get tackled was because wage
inflation was coming down.
But, if the labor market starts to
tighten back up, that could lead to
fears about wage inflation going back
up, which could then lead to headline
inflation going back up.
Yes, it pulled back.
So what, right? I mean,
it's not like we've never seen a spike
before where inflation didn't pull back
before going higher.
Um like, I mean, look at look at this
over here in the '70s. It spiked up to
7%, came back down to 6.2,
and then still ran to 14. So, this time
we've spiked up to 4.1 and we back we
drop back down to 3 and 1/2.
You know, you have to wonder
is the Fed
should are should they have raised rates
today? And if you look
at the two-year yield,
then I think absolutely they probably
should have raised rates today. But,
while they should have,
we still put out the video yesterday,
this video right here,
saying they wouldn't, right? Saying they
likely wouldn't. And
what what and this actually is is key to
look at this. Look at the probability of
a rate hike
or the probability that rates would be
at 4% by September.
Or let's say that the probably they
won't be at 4%. Only 23% chance.
Now that we had
this press release,
now that we had the press conference by
Kevin Warsh,
where is it now? It was 23% chance that
the Fed would still be at 3.75
by that September meeting.
Now,
by the September meeting, almost a 43%
chance they'll still be at three three
and point 75%.
So, it's not just
that they didn't hike rates, but now
market participants are not as sure that
they're going to hike rates in
September.
So, what and and Kevin Warsh even talked
about He said that rates were going up,
right? Long end was going up.
It is.
And if if the bond market
thinks that the Fed isn't going to get a
handle on this thing and if they're not
going to hike rates, there's only one
direction for the for yields to go, and
it's up.
They have to go somewhere. They're
either going to trend up or down.
They trend down more so when when
there's fears in the economy and and and
you think and markets think that we're,
you know, too tight. But right now
that's not the case. And you might say,
well, why do they need to raise rates?
What's really changed?
The neutral rate
is arguably what changed. Now, the
neutral rate is an abstract concept,
right? Like it's not there's not like a
clear
definition of of like what the neutral
rate even is.
You know, is it 3%? Is it 2%? Is it 4?
Is it 5?
Good luck finding a consensus on that.
But I think, as well as many others, I
think that one of the best
approximations we have for the neutral
rate is the two-year yield.
In fact, for modern portfolio theory and
calculating out the Sharpe ratio or the
Sortino ratio, a lot of times people
might use the two-year yield as the
risk-free rate.
So, when you look at the two-year yield,
back in March, the two-year yield was at
3.4%.
So, when you have rates at 3.75%,
that's theoretically restrictive because
it's higher than the neutral rate. The
idea is that when the Fed funds rate is
higher than the neutral rate, the the
market start the economy starts to
contract. When the Fed funds rate is
lower than the neutral rate, the economy
starts to expand. So, you could argue
that back over here in early 2026, let
me overlay
um
interest rates on the here. We'll we'll
put this on the the scale.
You could argue that back over here
we were not
restrictive.
Or sorry, no. You could argue that we
were restrictive. My mistake. You could
argue that
we were restrictive
because
the two-year yield
was below
the Fed funds rate.
So, restrictive.
But, look.
That's not the case anymore. The
two-year yield went up, thereby meaning
the neutral rate has theoretically gone
up if you believe that the two-year
yield is a good approximation of it. And
if the two-year yield is an
approximation of the neutral rate,
then the Fed funds rate is no longer
restrictive.
It's actually
more accommodative than it was a few
months ago, even though rates did not
change.
So, remember, the neutral rate is a
moving target.
And if you look if you zoom out
throughout history, the Fed chases the
two-year yield. Look at this. The Fed
chases the two-year yield. The two-year
yield tells the Fed what to do.
Fed does not tell the two-year yield
what to do. The market tells the Fed.
And you can see there's plenty of times
where the two-year yield goes up and it
takes a while for the Fed to get the
memo. But, look.
The two-year yield overtook the Fed
funds rate back in March.
It's taken them a while to get the memo.
I think they're going to get the memo.
I would argue September is a likely time
for them to raise rates. I'm not 100%
confident about it, but if you made me
pick a month, if you just said what is
the highest likelihood month if we're
going to get a rate hike this year, what
is the most likely month it's going to
be?
September could be it. I mean October
could as well, but
probably one of the next 3 months,
right? Like I I I think there will be a
rate hike in 2026. It's just a matter of
what month is it going to be? Is it
going to be September, October, or
December? And there's a lot of people
that think that they won't raise rates
before the midterms, but I would say
they they could. A lot of people thought
they wouldn't cut rates for the midterms
and they still before the presidential
election in 2024 and they still did. And
they say, "Well, this is different
because why would they raise rates?"
Uh you know, why would the
administration theoretically be okay
with that? Well, theoretically they are
not intertwined, even though that's
obviously debatable. But more
importantly, right? And this is is sort
of the more important aspect of it, is
that you could argue that a rate hike
wouldn't be nearly as much damaging
as inflation coming back and people
realizing the Fed's not going to do
anything to stop it.
What would the incumbents prefer? Would
they prefer to be seen fighting
inflation?
Or would they prefer to be seen letting
inflation run rampant? Remember, the two
major things that lead to incumbents
losing are inflation coming you know,
inflation surging and recessions. Think
about it, the last two presidential
elections were lost because of those two
issues, arguably. Biden lost after an
inflationary wave. Trump lost the
election before after a recession. Yes,
it was due to a pandemic. I'm not going
to pretend like the pandemic was was
Trump's fault, right? I mean it it was
going to happen regardless of who was in
office, but the markets don't care. If
you have a recession near the election,
the incumbent often loses. If inflation
is an issue near the election, the
incumbent often loses.
So, you could argue that
refusing to raise rates might actually
be more damaging
than raising them.
Because
what's going to happen in the midterms
if inflation's coming back and people
realize, "Whoa, the powers that that are
in office right now aren't going to do
anything to stop it." So, they want to
vote them out because no one likes
inflation.
So, it's a really interesting time in
markets. I I'm fairly confident I could
be wrong. I'm fairly confident they will
raise rates once and I think it's going
to correspond to this like 10 to 20%
drop in stocks that I think is going to
happen. Remember,
three midterm years,
2014, 2018, 2022, every midterm year for
the last three,
the market dropped 10 to 20%.
Near the end of
um
2014,
right, sorry. Yeah.
Let me go to the weekly. So, if you look
at at the end of uh 2014, over here,
10%.
End of 2018, 20%. End of 2022, 20%. They
started in the August to September time
frame.
There was another time the market
dropped about 10% and that was in from
starting in July of 2023 into October of
2023. Guess what that corresponded to.
Pause the video and guess. What did the
drop in late 20 It started in July 2023.
What did it correspond to?
You got it.
Well, at least I hope you did.
It was the 10-year yield
going crazy.
So, what this means
is if the 10-year yield is about to go
up again and the 30-year yield's already
breaking out, then yields are headed
higher. And wouldn't it be interesting
if the 30-year if the 10-year yield
started going up and tops in October,
which is exactly when it found that top
in 2023, guess what else October has in
common? Potentially a market cycle
bottom for Bitcoin. I mean, I guess I'm
not saying you need a narrative, but the
narrative is there. And I don't know
what people are going to blame later
this year, but it's all there on the
charts, okay? It's all there.
We'll see if it's right, but I think
that all this makes the most amount of
sense and and we talked about this
yesterday. We've been talking about it
forever. The Fed's unwilling to raise
rates, the bond market revolts, yields
go higher, the market corrects.
When the market corrects, it makes
people realize they're not going to
raise rates forever, right? They're not
raising rates back up to 5 and 1/2% more
than likely anytime soon. And then
cooler heads prevail and then hopefully
the market can start doing well again,
you know, going into 2027. So, the
narrative is there if you need one, but
you really really do not need one. If
you guys like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up. And again, check out the
Investing Through the Cycles Conference
taking place
uh in Miami November 20th through the
22nd. Make sure you guys get a ticket. I
look forward to seeing you guys there.
Thank you for tuning in. I will see you
next time. Bye.